这是凝聚态课程的第六讲
this is a the sixth lecture of the
condensed matter course
在上一讲中，我们讨论了离子键和共价键的键合以及
in last lecture we discussed bonding
ionic bonding and covalent bonding and
还有其他三种类型的绑定，它们在我们要列出的列表中
there were three other types of bonding
they were on a list that we were going
最终覆盖范德华键合金属键合和氢
to cover eventually van der Waals
bonding metallic bonding and hydrogen
绑定，由于种种原因，我将把这些推迟到以后
bonding and for various reasons I'm
going to push those off until later
我们将尝试将它们放到适合的位置，而我们要做的是
we'll try to pick them up where they fit
in instead what we're gonna do is we're
要回去重新考虑原子的运动，我们要简化你的生活
gonna go back and reconsider the motion
of atoms we're gonna simplify your life
今天很多，我们只考虑一个原子的运动
an awful lot today and we're only going
to consider the motion of atoms in one
维度，所以今天我们生活在一个一维的世界中
dimension so for the purpose of today we
live in a one-dimensional world we're
我们将非常简单地总结一下我们所了解的有关粘接的所有信息
gonna summarize everything we know about
bonding very simply we're going to
想象我们有两个原子相距一段距离X，
imagine we have two atoms some distance
apart what's called a distance X and
X的势能V代表
there will be some potential V of X
which represents the force between the
我们上次讨论的X的两个原子和X的电位V可能看起来
two atoms and the potential V of X as we
discussed last time it probably looks
X的V之类的东西，所以它具有吸引人的结合
something like this V of X something
like that so it has a attractive bonding
力，然后如果原子距离太近，势能会突然上升
force and then if the atoms get too
close the potential shoots off to
无限好，所以我们通常要做的就是扩展
infinity okay so what we're usually
going to do is we're going to expand
围绕这个最小值的底部以二次方的方式将其近似为
around the bottom of this minimum in a
quadratic way and approximate it as a
抛物线，所以我们将X的V表示为V等于V等于V等于底V
parabola so we'll write V of X is some V
naught V naught is the bottom V naught
在这里加上它的距离
here
plus it's called this distance here from
这里到这里，我们称X平衡为
here to here let's call that X
equilibrium that's the the bottom of the
换句话说，原子最想坐的距离
well in other words the distance at
which the atoms would most like to sit
能量的最小值，因此想在此处给出一个二次项X减去X
the minimum of the energy so would like
to give a quadratic term here X minus X
平衡平方加点点点好，所以如果两个
equilibrium squared plus dot dot dot
okay so the energy is minimum if the two
原子被这个平衡距离分开，然后是某种
atoms are separated by this equilibrium
distance and then it's some sort of
抛物线，如果原子更远或更近
parabola if you if the atoms are either
farther apart or closer together okay
现在我们在执行此操作时应谨慎一些，因为偶尔
now we should be a little bit cautious
in doing this because occasionally by
近似抛物线，你把婴儿扔出去
approximating something
parabola you throw the baby out with the
沐浴水，尤其是如果您担心热膨胀，
bathwater and in particular if you're
worried about thermal expansion it's
保持点对点术语非常重要，事实上，
very important to keep the dot-dot-dot
terms the fact that in fact the
潜力不是抛物线，所以让我们考虑一下
potential is not a parabola so let's
think about that for a second
如果原子处于低温状态，热膨胀如何发生？
how does thermal expansion happen well
if you're at low temperature the atoms
您有点想像潜在阱底部的粒子，但是
you sort of think of a like a particle
in the bottom of potential well but
我们真正在谈论的是两个原子之间的距离
we're really talking about is the
distance between the two the two atoms
但是您可以考虑一下来回摆动的距离
but you can sort of think about that
distance oscillating back and forth just
就像是井底的粒子，所以它来回摆动
like it was a particle in the bottom of
well so it oscillates back and forth the
原子变得越来越远，越来越近，它们来回振荡
atoms get farther apart and closer
together they oscillate back and forth
并且平均距离几乎保持在X平衡，但是如果我们给
and pretty much the average distance
stays at X equilibrium but if we give
原子的能量更高，温度比原子高
the atoms some higher amount of energy
here a higher temperature then the atoms
可以摆动到这里，但一直到这里都可以，因为
can oscillate into here but out all the
way to here okay because the the
内部的电势比外部的电势陡
potential is steeper on the inside than
it is on the outside
通常，原子将能够使其在此处达到此x max和此X min X
generally the atoms will be able to make
it far this x max here and this X min X
最小值将与X平衡值不同，特别是X Max Plus X
min will differ a different amount from
X equilibrium in particular X Max Plus X
在2上的最小值将大于在T等于零时的X平衡，因此
min over two will be greater than X
equilibrium at T equals zero so the
原子开始振荡时彼此之间的平均距离
average distance that the atoms are from
each other when they start oscillating
将会开始增加，这是由于以下事实：
will start to increase and this comes
from the fact that when the when the
原子振荡，它们可以推动一点点，但潜力确实是
atoms oscillate they can push in a
little bit but the potential is really
陡峭的，所以他们不能推那么多，但是当他们振荡出
steep so they can't push in that much
but then when they oscillate out the
势较弱，所以他们可以走得更远，所以这就是
potential is softer so they can go much
farther distance out so this is what
为您提供热膨胀的潜在形式
gives you thermal expansion the
particular form of the potential
原子彼此远离并变得非常非常柔软的功能
function that's softer as the atoms go
away from each other and gets very very
当原子彼此靠近时陡峭，但是只要我们不
steep when the atoms get close to each
other okay but as long as we're not
考虑热膨胀之类的事情，可以截断我们的
considering things like thermal
expansion it's okay to just truncate our
二次方的势，我们有一个纯胡克定律类型的弹簧
potential at quadratic order and we have
a pure Hookes law type spring between
到目前为止，我们的原子还不错，每个人都满意，好吗？
our atoms so far so good
everyone happy with that okay so what
我们将在本讲座的其余部分中讲到，
we're going to do with the rest of the
lecture is we're going to take a very
原子振动的简单模型实际上是
simple model of atomic vibration
actually extremely simple model of
原子振动，称为单原子单原子谐波链
atomic vibration which is known as the
monatomic monatomic harmonic chain
谐波链可能是我们要使用的最重要的模型
harmonic chain which is potentially the
most important model we're going to
全年学习不仅因为它碰巧出现在期末考试中
study all year not only because it
happens to show up on the final exams
如此频繁的单原子意味着只有一种类型的原子谐波
very frequently so monatomic means that
there is only one type of atom harmonic
意味着它将是原子和链之间的简单弹簧
means that it's going to be just simple
Springs between the atoms and chains
意味着我们会有很多这样的原子，原因很简单
mean we're gonna have a lot of these
atoms and the reason it's a very simple
模型，但之所以如此重要，是因为它引入了很多想法
model but the reason it's so important
is because it introduces a lot of ideas
在整个学期中都会反复出现
that will come back over and over again
throughout the term so this is what it
看起来我们有一堆原子，我们又生活在一个维度中
looks like we have a bunch of atoms and
again we're living in one dimension the
排成一排的每个原子都有一些质量M，它们全部相同，然后
lined up in a row each atom has some
mass M all of them identical and then
有一个弹簧常数，所有弹簧常数之间完全相同
there's a spring constant all the spring
constants identical identical between
两个原子Kappa Kappa Kappa和Kappa的弹簧常数来自
the two atoms Kappa Kappa Kappa and the
Kappa the spring constant comes from the
键电位的扩展我们的谐波扩展
expansion of the of the bonding
potential the harmonic expansion that we
没关系用完两者之间的平衡距离
used up above okay
the equilibrium distance between the two
原子X平衡在这里我们称其为
atoms X equilibrium here let's call it a
for the purpose of
通常在这里这个距离a的论点称为晶格
argument generally over here this
distance a is known as a lattice
常数，通常我们会经常使用晶格常数一词
constant and generally we're gonna use
the word lattice constant frequently
术语“晶格常数”的后面一般是指
later in the term lattice constant
general generally means distance between
在相同的原子之间，在这种情况下，我们所有的原子都是相同的，所以
between identical atoms and in this case
all of our atoms are identical so it's
只是这里原子之间的距离让我们在这里定义一些位置
just the distance between the atoms here
let's define some positions here so
我们称这个为一个x也许这个为X 2 X 3
let's call this one x one maybe this one
will be X 2 X 3
一般说X sub n是原子n的位置，让我们让X和
that so generally say that X sub n is
position of atom n and let's let X and
上标0是原子an的平衡位置，因此
the superscript 0 be the equilibrium
position position of atom an so that's
你想象让链条静止下来，然后测量位置
you imagine letting the the chain come
to rest and you measure the positions
它们之间的距离都是a，所以X和0就是
they're all spaced by a distance a so X
and 0 is just we can let it be if we let
如果原子从位置0开始则为0，那么我们可以将X和0设置为n乘以a
the 0 if atoms start at position 0 then
we can just set X and 0 to be n times a
每个原子与下一个原子之间的距离为a，而实际上我们是
each atom separated by a distance a from
the next and the quantity we're actually
感兴趣的是与平衡位置的偏差，我们称之为
interested in is the deviation from the
equilibrium position which we'll call
Delta X，所以Delta X sub n是X sub n减去xn naught，我们要做的是
Delta X so Delta X sub n is X sub n
minus xn naught and what we're going to
尝试做的是，我们将尝试找出该链条的振动
try to do is we're going to try to
figure out the vibrations of this chain
首先使用完全经典的物理学，我们将担心量子
using completely classical physics to
begin with and we'll worry about quantum
物理之后，所以您可能已经完成了耦合
physics later
so in you've probably done coupled
第一年可能会有春天和质量问题，这很漂亮
spring and mass problems probably in
your first year and it's pretty
你应该做的很简单，就是你应该写下来
straightforward what you're supposed to
do is you're supposed to write down
牛顿方程适用于所有质量，所以很容易我们有了F
Newton's equations for all of the masses
so that's pretty easy we just have F
等于MA，所以原子n上的f是质量乘以加速度Delta X的两倍
equals MA so f on the atom n is mass
times the acceleration Delta X double
点，那么第n个质量上的X上的力是多少
dot and so what is the force on on X on
on the nth mass well okay it has a force
从原子到它的右边，所以它是Kappa Hookes定律Delta X n加1减去Delta
from the atom to its right so it's Kappa
Hookes law Delta X n plus 1 minus Delta
X n，然后它在左边的Kappa Delta X上受到原子的作用力为负
X n and then it has a force from the
atom on its left Kappa Delta X and minus
1减去Delta X，我想我们可以通过写简化一下
1 minus Delta X and I guess we can
simplify that a little bit by writing is
Kappa Delta X和加1加Delta X和减1减2 Delta X和
Kappa Delta X and plus 1 plus Delta X
and minus 1 minus 2 Delta X and
我们要解决的是我们要解决普通模式
and what we'd like to solve for is we
would like to solve for the normal modes
想要此链正常模式的正常模式，提醒您意味着所有
want-want normal modes of this chain
normal mode to remind you means all
原子以相同的频率假设在相同的频率，如果您还记得
atoms postulate at a common frequency at
common frequency and if you remember how
您在第一年的课程中做到了这一点，最终将成为
you did this in in your first-year
courses it would ended up being an
具有质量数维矩阵的特征值问题
eigenvalue problem with sort of a matrix
the dimension of the number of masses
如果我们现在拥有的话，我们可能会有无数的群众要处理
you have now we might have an infinite
number of masses here to deal with if we
有一个很长的链，所以它看起来像一个无限大的特征值问题
have a very long chain so it looks like
an infinitely large eigenvalue problem
听起来可能有点吓人，但事实证明
and that might be sound a little bit
frightening but it turns out that
解决这样的问题真的很容易，我们将再次使用
solving problems like this is really
easy and we're gonna do again we use the
一年又一年，都是同样的把戏，把戏是猜测
same kind of trick over and over this
year and the trick is to guess the
回答，幸运的是所有的猜测
answer
and fortunately the guesses are all the
一样，所以很容易猜到猜测是您使用了点波
same so it's easy to guess the guess is
you use what is known as a wave on dots
点上是德语单词，意思是猜测，所以我们要
on dots is a german word that means
something like guess so we're gonna
猜想解决方案是波形，有人会说德语
guess that the solutions are waveforms
someone who speaks german is probably
说不，那不是什么意思，就是你说的是的，我有
saying no it's that's not what it means
is that what you're saying yeah I have
不知道这是什么经验法则或什么意思，我可以接受
no idea what does it mean rule of thumb
or something it means what okay I stand
纠正物理我们经常很好地谢谢你
corrected
thank you well in physics we frequently
我们用它来表示猜测
we use it to mean to mean guess
所以我不知道它到底来自哪里，所以诀窍是我们要
so I don't know where it came from all
right so so the trick is we're going to
猜想振荡的形式是简单的波，所以
guess that that the the the form of the
of the oscillations are simple waves so
我们将为波形写下Delta X是I Omega t的常数ae
we'll write down a for a wave form Delta
X is some constant a e to the I Omega t
减去IK乘以X，而不是K，这里是波矢，而Omega是频率
minus I K times X and not K here is the
wave vector and Omega is the frequency
现在这可能有点令人困惑，因为我们写下来的是
now this might be a little bit confusing
because what we've written down is we've
写下一些复杂的内容，据我们所知，这些职位感兴趣
written down something complex where as
we know the positions were interested in
实际上是真实的，但这就像当您知道学习电路
are actually real but this is just like
when you you know study circuits in your
第一年，您试图考虑的是振荡电流，
first year you're trying to think about
currents that are oscillating and
而不是写正弦和余弦，而是写下一些复杂的东西
instead of writing sines and cosines you
write down some sort of complex
表达，而你真正的意思是你应该把真实
expression and what you really mean is
that you're supposed to take to the real
在一天的结尾部分，这就是我们真正的意思是在这里结束
part at the end of the day and that's
what we really mean here is at the end
一天之内您应该参与其中，而我们这样做的原因是
of the day you should take the real part
and the reason we do this is because
使用指数的总是比使用指数的容易
it's always easier to work with
Exponential's than it is to work with
现在是正弦和余弦，因为我们将尽我们所能
sines and cosines now because we're
going to take the real part we could put
在指数中减去整体负号后仍会得到相同的答案，因此我们可以
an overall minus sign up in the exponent
and still get the same answer so we can
修复Omega始终大于或等于零
fix that Omega is always greater than or
equal to zero
不失一般性，因为如果您只是更改符号
without any loss of generality because
if you just change the sign of
一切和指数一旦您发挥了真正的作用，您最终就会得到
everything and the exponent once you
take the real part you end up getting
结果相同，但我们必须跟踪K可以有一个正弦的事实
the same result but we must keep track
of the fact that K can have either sine
好吧，要么是正弦波，要么是向左波，要么是向右波
okay either sine which corresponds to
either a left going wave or a right
我想我们应该在这里替代另一件事
going wave the other thing I guess we
should probably substitute in here the
xn的值为零，这是n倍，所以我们要做的就是
value of xn zero which is n times a okay
so then all we have to do is we have to
在Zots上接受这一浪潮，将其插入牛顿方程
take this wave on Zots
plug it into Newton's equations up there
看看如果我们将其插入左侧，我们会很好
and see what we get all right well if we
plug it in on the left hand side we get
减去M Omega平方乘以P至I Omega T
minus M Omega squared times a P to the I
Omega T
好的，衍生权使负的Omega平方下降，然后在
okay and a right to derivatives brings
down minus Omega squared and then on the
右手边，我们得到Kappa，是的，Kappa到我有一个e
right hand side we get Kappa a
yeah okay Kappa a there's an e to the I
Omega T是所有术语通用的，然后我们得到e减去IK
Omega T which is common to all the terms
and then we get e to the minus I K and
负IK n加上1 a加e n负1 a负2唯一的ikna好现在我们
plus 1 a plus e to the minus I K n minus
1 a minus 2 unique i k n a good now we
可以从这个方程式中消除很多事情来简化我们的生活
can cancel out a whole bunch of things
from this equation to simplify our life
所以我们得到负的MΩ平方等于I的Kappa e加上负的e
so we get minus M Omega squared equals
Kappa e to the i ka plus e to the minus
IK减2，那么我们可以使用Trig Identity来确定这个东西实际上是2
I K a minus 2 then we can use a trig
identity that this thing is actually 2
倍余弦，实际上我也将它们移到另一边
times the cosine and I actually move
them to the other side as well we get
欧米茄平方，它是Kappa / M 2减去2余弦ka
omega squared
it's Kappa / M 2 minus 2 cosine ka
另一个三角身份，我们可以将1减去余弦K a替换为正弦
another trig identity that we can
replace 1 minus cosine K a as sine
超过2的ka的平方，这样一来我们总共有4个，而ya总共有4 K超过m
squared of ka over 2 so that gives us a
total of 4 with ya total of 4 K over m
将ka的正弦平方乘以2，然后我将取平方根
times sine squared of ka over 2 and then
I'll just take the square root of this
整个方程式，我们得到的最终结果Ω是m上Kappa的2平方根
whole equation we get the final result
Omega is 2 square root of Kappa over m
正弦K的绝对值超过2，我们已经解决了
absolute value of sine K over 2 and
there we have it we've we solved for the
给定波矢，链的正常模式的频率现在可以了
frequency of the normal modes of our
chain given the wave vector okay now
可能值得绘制答案去，所以看起来像这样，我们在这里
probably worth plotting the answer
go so was it looked like so here we have
垂直的K的欧米茄，然后像这样水平放置K，我们将
Omega of K vertically then we have K
horizontally okay like this and we'll
提出一些要点，让我们对此点进行PI，也许这是
put some points on let's make this point
PI over a maybe this point over here is
在a上减去PI，我们得到正弦类型外观的正弦绝对值
minus PI over a and we have this sine
absolute value of sine kind of looks
像这样的正弦绝对值看起来像这样，好吧，
like this absolute value of sine kind of
looks like this that okay well there's
应该是相同的高度，这条曲线的高度是平方
supposed to be the same height and the
height of this curve here is to square
K的根超过m，并且在PI超过a时达到峰值，而在a超过PI时达到峰值，因此
root of K over m and it has its peak at
PI over a and at minus PI over a so this
曲线称为弥散曲线弥散曲线
curve is known as a dispersion curve
dispersion dispersion
只是表示欧米茄是K的函数
it just means Omega as a function of K
现在在这张图片的某个地方，我们应该期望会有声波
now somewhere in this picture we should
expect that there should be sound waves
想着谈论一些固体的振荡，我的意思是我们有这个
with think talking about oscillations of
some solid I mean we have this we have
我们的固体图片，就是原子与弹簧粘在一起，
our picture of a solid which is just
atoms stuck together with Springs and
某处应该有一些像声波的东西
somewhere in there there should be
something that looks like sound waves
声波在哪里好声波是很长的波长
where are the sound waves well sound
wave is a very long wavelength
现象声音的定义是应该是长波长
phenomenon the definition of sound is
that it should be a long wavelength
振荡，所以我们真的应该在这里小K处寻找
oscillation so we should really be
looking down here at small K to look for
声波只是作为您所知道的助记符
sound waves just to as a you know sort
of mnemonic the sound that you hear has
波长介于一厘米到几米之间
wavelength somewhere between like a
centimeter and several meters that's
您可以听到的声音取决于您耳朵的音质，而
what you can you can hear depending on
how good your ears are whereas the
我们在上面讨论这个pi的原子之间的间距是一个o如此
spacing between atoms that we're talking
about this pi over a a here one o is so
在波矢量上与此pi关联的波长约为
this the wavelength associated with this
pi over a wave vector is on the order of
出现的原子之间的距离还可以，所以波上有2 pi
the distance between atoms okay with a
appears here so 2 pi over the wave
向量会给你一个原子间距的数字，所以
vector will give you a number on the
order of the spacing between atoms so
这张照片的大部分是非常非常非常小的波长
most of this picture is very very very
small wavelength compared
我们通常认为他的声音是针对非常小的波长的
what we usually think of his sound sound
is for very very small wavelengths right
靠近K的中间等于零，所以我们实际上尝试找出
down near the middle near K equals zero
so let's actually try to figure out what
声音将按照我们弄清楚声音在做什么的方式进行
到K非常接近于零我们扩展了这个东西我们扩展了符号然后我们最终
to K very close to zero we expand this
thing we expand the sign and we end up
得到什么我们会好起来的1/2取消2，我们得到的平方根
getting what do we get well the 1/2
cancels the 2 and we get square root of
Kappa超过m乘以绝对K的倍数，您会记得
Kappa over m times a times absolute K
and you'll remember the definition of
声速是频率应该是声速乘以绝对值
the sound velocity is that frequency
should be sound velocity times absolute
K，因此我们得出的声速是m乘以a的Kappa的平方根
K and so we've derived sound velocity is
square root of Kappa over m times a
如果您上学期参加了流体课程，那么我们现在的声速
there we have our sound velocity now if
you took the fluids course last term
您会记住，声音也可以用诸如
you'll remember that sound can also be
defined in terms of things like
流体的可压缩性，我们应该能够获得相同的速度
compressibility of a fluid and we should
be able to get the same velocity of the
从公式中得出的声音是您得出的上一项是1以上的平方根
sound from the formula that you derive
last term which is square root of 1 over
密度质量密度这里的质量密度乘以β的可压缩性还可以
density mass density here mass density
times the beta the compressibility okay
那么我们的链条的质量密度是多少，这很容易
so what's the mass density of our chain
that's easy it's just one mass per
距离a，首先要压缩的是什么
distance a and what's the
compressibility well first we have to
弄清楚可压缩性的定义是V减去-1
figure out what the definition of
compressibility is it's minus 1 over V
体积和压力，但我们处于一维，因此被负号代替
the volume and pressure but we're in 1
dimension so that gets replaced by minus
1超过长度D的长度D的力，因此，如果您考虑其中的一小部分
1 over length D length D force so if you
think about one little piece of the
链的长度为1，长度为a，则您从胡克斯（Hookes）延伸森林长度
chain the length is 1 over a length is a
and you length the forest from Hookes
定律是Kappa的负1，所以可压缩性是Kappa的1
law is minus 1 over Kappa so the
compressibility is just 1 over Kappa a
然后如果我们将这两个表达式插入那好吧
and then if we plug in these two
expressions into that well okay well do
然后在此以这种可压缩性使用质量密度为1
it here this is then using this mass
density in this compressibility it's 1
超过a的质量，然后所有Kappa都超过Kappa a，这使我们
over mass over a and then all Kappa oops
one over Kappa a and that gives us in
事实与我们在这里得到的结果相同
fact the same result that we had over
here
kappa超过m倍a，因此与我们从a得到的表达式一致
kappa over m times a so it agrees with
the expression we would get from a
声波应该没有问题的流体力学图片
hydrodynamic picture of what sound waves
should be okay so everything all sorts
似乎工作得很好，但是在这种情况下，它的作用是
seems to work pretty well but that is
way down here in this regime with a
在较高的k处色散是线性的，它不再是线性的
where the dispersion is linear
at higher k it's not linear anymore it
开始弯曲，现在回想起德拜在说德拜是
starts to curve now think back to what
it was that Debye was saying Debye was
说他只是假设他的声音模式的频率是
saying he was going to just assume that
the the frequency of his sound modes was
总是在K线性，然后他以某个最大频率切断频谱
always linear in K and then he cut off
the spectrum at some maximum frequency
好吧，它开始是线性的，它不会保持线性曲线，但是确实
well it starts out linear it doesn't
stay linear curves but indeed it does
最大频率高于某个频率，就没有声音模式了
have a maximum frequency above some
frequency there's no sound modes left we
找到了系统的所有正常模式，这就是所有这些，而且它们具有
found all of the normal modes of the
system this is all of them and they have
只有能量，它们的频率只有零到这个频率之间，所以
only energy they only have frequencies
between zero and this frequency here so
在这方面，德拜是对的，确实存在最大声波
Debye was right in that respect that
there really is a maximum sound wave
频率不是很好的称为声音，而是您的振动频率
frequency it's not well mudan called
sound but your vibrational frequency of
在这一点上，值得在此更仔细地研究一下
this chain it's worth looking a little
bit more closely at this point here
这是最高频率激励的最高频率正常模式
which is the highest frequency
excitation highest frequency normal mode
所以发生在K等于PI超过a，我们将如何看待更多
so that occurs at K equals PI over a and
how are we gonna look at that more
很好，让我们写下波形对我来说是什么
closely well let's let's write down what
the wave form would be it's a e to the I
Ω减去I PI超过I倍，否则将成为IΩT倍
Omega t minus I PI over a times a n or
it would be a into the I Omega T times
负1到N表示每个交替的偶数与奇数质量都在移动
minus 1 to the N which means that every
alternate even versus odd mass is moving
相反的方向，这是您可能获得的最高频率
in the opposite direction and that's the
highest frequency you can possibly get
好吧，现在值得看一部电影
okay
at this point it's worth seeing a movie
所以，让我，哦，在这里，我们今天看看它是否可以正常工作
so let me uh-oh here we go
see if it works today beautiful okay
这是我们可以从我的网站下载的程序，它是由Mike编写的
so this is a program we can download
from my website it was written by Mike
Glazer可以在Windows上运行，可以在Linux上的Wine下运行，我认为可能
Glazer it works on Windows it works
under wine on Linux I think it probably
在Mac上可以使用，但我不确定
works on on Mac but I'm not sure about
that
因此，如果它的目的是向您展示其中之一的振荡
so the the its if the purpose of it is
to show you what oscillations of one of
这些链实际上看起来很详细，因此在这里我们单击单原子链
these chains actually looks like in
detail so here we click monatomic chain
我们将点击纵向，这意味着天哪，我改变了速度
and we're gonna click longitudinal which
means oops my gosh change the speed
我们去了，所以您也可以更改振荡速度以使其更容易
there we go so you can change the speed
of oscillation as well to make it easier
看看我们在这个角落有什么
to see so what we have here in this
corner
在这里，您具有色散曲线，可以从
over here you have this dispersion curve
and you can change K back and forth from
你知道高K工具好吧，所以让我们从一个非常低K吧开始吧，
you know high K tool okay so let's start
with a very fairly low K okay make the
速度相当快，所以您可以看到这里发生的事情，还可以看到
speed fairly fast so you can see what's
going on here okay and you can see at
相当低的K来吧，你可以看到这是一个很长的波长
fairly low K come on yeah you can see
that this is sort of a long wavelength
每个人向左摆动然后向右摆动以及向后摆动的振荡
oscillation where everyone sloshes left
then sloshes to the right and back and
随着K的增加，它来回振荡得更快，
forth and back and forth now as we
increase K it oscillates faster and
更快，波长变得越来越小，直到最终
faster and the wavelength gets gets
smaller and smaller and until eventually
它的振荡速度真的非常快，我不得不放慢速度
it's oscillating really really fast and
I'm gonna have to slow down the speed so
您实际上可以了解到在这一点上进行PI时发生了什么
you can actually see what's going on
when you get to PI over a this point
在这里，您可以看到其他所有质量都朝相反的方向前进，
here you can see that every other mass
is going in the opposite direction and
如果您考虑了一会儿，您将意识到这是一个很好的选择
if you think about it for a while you'll
realize that this is there's a good
这是您可能获得的最高频率的原因
reason why this is the highest frequency
that you can possibly get
你不能做得比其他所有人都反对它的邻居更好
that you can't do any better than having
every other mass opposing its neighbor
如果您想获得很高的压缩率或高频，这就是
that if you want to get really high
compression or high frequency this is
您可能会遇到的最高频率，所以我将其留给你们
the highest frequency you could possibly
get okay so I'll leave that for you guys
玩，我建议把它弄乱
to play with
I recommend messing around with it a
一点点，呃，我们将在将Beca再次推向所有人时遇到问题
little bit uh-oh we're gonna have
problems turning Beca that back on all
好吧，所以最重要的是
right anyway
good so the most important thing that we
我们在此计算中得出的是，色散在K中是周期性的
that we deduced in this calculation is
that the dispersion is periodic in K
它与一个符号成比例，您会看到，您知道色散
it was proportional to a sign and you'll
see that you know the the dispersion
只是一遍又一遍地不断地像自己一样前进
just keeps going exactly like itself
over and over we sort of a periodicity
你知道从这里到这里，你只是不断地替换它
you know from here to here you just keep
replacing over and over it looks exactly
同样，这不是巧合，有一个普遍的法律，如果你有
the same this is not a coincidence
there's a general law that if you have
在现实空间中是周期性的，在现实空间中，例如具有
something that's periodic in real space
real space like a chain which has a
如果您采用了我们的整个链，并且您转移了，则周期性周期Delta x等于a
periodic periodicity Delta x equals a if
you take our whole chain and you shifted
如果有东西，您将再次返回完全相同的链
over by a you get back exactly the same
chain again if you have uh something
在现实空间中是周期性的，我也应该说现实空间也是已知的
that's periodic in real space I should
also say that real space is also known
作为直接空间直接空间意味着您将具有分散
as direct space direct space that will
imply that you have a dispersion which
是周期的，并且k空间中的K也称为具有周期的倒数空间
is periodic and K in k space also known
as reciprocal space with a periodicity
Delta K的a等于a的2pi，因此名称倒数，因为这里a
of Delta K equals 2pi over a and hence
the name reciprocal because here the a
在楼上，这里的a在楼下，现在这是一些
is upstairs and here the a is is
downstairs now the periodic here's some
一些更多有用的词，这里的周期单位是已知的
some more words that are going to be
useful the periodic unit here is known
作为棕熊区1区，也许我会写一些定义
as the Bruins zone 1 zone maybe I'll
write that definition a little bit is
这相当重要，k空间中k空间中的周期单位等于棕熊
this rather important the periodic unit
in k space in k space equals the Bruins
我自己，我不仅向讲德语的人道歉，而且向
own and I apologize
not only to German speakers but to
现在讲法语的人说，右侧Louie Dubrow上的这个扫帚是
French speakers now that the this word
broom on the right Louie Dubrow on is a
说英语的人很难正确发音的单词
word that English speakers have a
terribly hard time pronouncing correctly
可能会讲法语的人都会畏缩于
and probably anyone who speaks French
will cringe at how
我屠杀它，但我不是每个讲英语的人中唯一的一个
I butcher it but I'm not the only one
every English speaker
屠夫这个名字我真的很抱歉我在法国差点失败。
butchers this name I really apologize
about that I almost failed French in
高中，所以我从来没有做得更好，但我认为这是
high school so I've never gotten any
better at it but I think it's something
就像布里恩·旺（Brie Whan）一样，这是我现在最好的猜测
like brie whan that's my best guess
about how it's supposed to be okay now
为什么这是一个非常重要的原则，我们在
why is it this is a very important
principle that we have periodicity in
k空间为什么我们在k空间具有周期性
k-space why is it we have periodicity in
k-space
好，让我们找出我们的波形Delta xn是I Omega t的ae
well let's find out we have our wave
form Delta xn is a e to the I Omega t
减去IK na，然后取K并将其偏移2 pi
minus I K na and then let's take K and
shift it by 2 pi over a shift it by this
从这里到这里的整个长度，我们将取一个特定的K并将其移动2
entire length from here to here we'll
take some particular K and move it by 2
pi在a上，看看为什么我们能很好地返回同一件事，让我们将e转换为
pi over a and see why we get back the
same thing well let's do that shift e to
我的I Omega T，然后我们得到负IK + 2 PI乘以na
the I Omega T and then we get minus I K
plus 2 PI over a times na and that
等于a等于I Omega T减去IK，乘以e等于负I 2 pi N和
equals a e to the I Omega T minus I K
and a times e to the minus I 2 pi N and
这个东西是1，所以实际上我们要返回完全相同的波形
this thing here is 1 so in fact we're
getting back exactly the same waveform
我们开始时色散曲线看起来与此相同的原因
that we started with the reason the
dispersion curve looks the same at this
在这里，这是因为他们正在准确地描述
point here and this point here is
because they're describing exactly the
相同的波，通过将K移2 pi可以使波保持不变，这是一个
same wave the wave is unchanged by
shifting K by 2 pi over a ok this is an
非常重要的原则，我们会一遍又一遍地重复
extremely important principle that we'll
come back over and over and over now
这可能会让您感到不安，从嗯开始吧
this might be something that you you'll
find disturbing to begin with uh-huh ok
现在我们在这里有问题，好吧，现在看看我能不能告诉你，糟糕
now we have a problem here ok now see if
I can show you this oops come back ok
让我向您展示其他东西，看看是否最终恢复正常，是的，很好，所以
let me show you something else see if it
comes back up eventually yes ok good so
您可能会问，在一个波长范围内，K是否等于k加2pi
you might ask well if K is the same as k
plus 2pi over a what's the wave length
对，我的意思是我们通常认为波长是2pi超过2pi
right I mean we usually think of the
wave length as being 2pi over a 2pi over
k等于波长2pi超过k等于2pi，所以如果K相同，则知道它是
k equals a wave length 2pi over k equals
so if K is the same you know which it's
在这里和这里在物理上是同一波波长是正确的
physically the same wave here and here
which one's the wavelength well the way
可以从这张照片中了解到，所以这里绘制了Delta X DX
to understand that is from this picture
here so Delta X DX here is plotted on
垂直轴只是为了使其更清楚，所以我在这里画了两个波
the vertical axis just to make it more
clear so I've plotted two waves here one
其中实线位于K或实际上该虚线为K且
of them the solid line is at K or
actually this dash line is K and the and
实线在ok处在k加2 pi处，两条曲线在该位置一致
the solid line is at k plus 2 pi over a
ok the two curves agree at the position
群众，我们只是在谈论群众的流离失所，
of the masses and we're only talking
about the displacement of the masses the
波形在质量位置之间不表示任何东西
wave doesn't mean anything in between
the position of the masses the wave form
是用来描述群众在做什么，你不能问
is meant to describe what the masses are
doing you can't ask what is the value of
群众之间的波浪没有价值，意味着波浪
the wave in between the masses it
doesn't have a value the wave is meant
描述海浪在做什么，群众在做什么
to describe what the waves are doing
what the what the masses are doing so it
您是否在实体中延伸曲线实际上并没有任何意义
doesn't actually mean anything whether
you extend the the curve in the solid
两个质量之间的直线或虚线，但仅此而已
line way or the dashed line way in
between the two masses but only all that
重要的是群众是多少，你知道个别群众有多少流离失所
matters is what the mass is you know how
much the individual masses are displaced
这是一种被称为锯齿的现象，如果您想到了这一点，您将
this is a phenomenon known as aliasing
and if you get this in your head you'll
很好地理解了为什么在这一点上，而这一点实际上是
understand pretty well why it is at this
point and this point are actually
即使他们有不同的洞穴，也可以描述同一波
describing the same wave even though
they have different caves okay good all
好吧好吧，这是Naumann clay Chur多了一点
right all right so it's a couple a
little bit more Naumann clay Chur that's
相当有用的实际空间晶格让我将其定义为所有点
fairly useful the real space lattice
lattice let me define it as all points
等效点
points equivalent
两个x等于零，所以在我们的图片中XN等于a的M倍
two x equals zero so in our picture
there that would be X N equals M times a
因为您可以在整个春季之前移动每个点，然后回到
because you can shift each point by
entire spring and you get back to
看起来完全一样的东西我们也有倒数的空间格
something that looks exactly the same we
also have the reciprocal space lattice
倒数空间我们饮的空间晶格是k中的所有点
reciprocal space we sip space lattice
which is all points in k space points in
等于k的k空间等于0，对于此特定模型，则为
k space equivalent to k equals 0 and for
this particular model it would then be
我们称这些点G sub M等于2 pi M在所有这些点上
let's call those points G sub M equals 2
pi M over a all those points are
等价于k等于0，在实际中，将2 pi的2 pi单位偏移了0
equivalent to k equals 0 shifted by 2 pi
units of 2 pi over a now it's actually
一些有趣的事情，将在今年晚些时候变得重要
something that is kind of interesting
and will be important later on this year
EBI GM xn在所有点上总是等于1，并且有直接
is the EBI GM xn is always equal to 1
for all of the points and there's direct
晶格和倒易晶格中的所有点，您可以选择
lattice and all the points in the
reciprocal lattice you can choose any
这些点的结合，实际上总会给你一个
combination of those points and will
always give you one in fact we're gonna
当我们使用更高的尺寸时，我们将使用该属性作为一种方式
use that when we go to higher dimensions
we're gonna use that property as a way
定义倒易格，所以把它放在你的脑后
to define the reciprocal lattice so sort
of put it in the back of your your head
因此，在这一点上，实际上对我们而言非常有用的一件事是
so one thing that's actually really
useful for us to do at this point is to
计算我们为正常波模求解的枚举波总数
count the total number of waves that we
enumerated we solved for normal modes of
该系统中有多少个它们？有多少个正常模式
the system so how many are them of them
are there how many how many normal modes
正常模式，我们知道如果我们要计算不同的正常模式，我们只会
normal modes well we know that if we're
counting different normal modes we only
不得不看一下布鲁因斯区域，那么如果我们走到格兰德区域之外，我们可以
have to look within the Bruins zone then
if we go outside the grande zone we can
总是我们描述的东西等同于
always we're describing something that's
equivalent to another point inside the
棕褐色区域，我们在此处选择此点，例如，它等同于此点
Bruins zone we pick this point here for
example its equivalent to this point
在这里，我们只需要描述*区域内的事物就可以了
here so we only have to describe things
within the bran zone we have to figure
找出*区域内有多少种模式，所以我们将做平常的事情
out how many modes there are within the
bran zone so we'll do the usual thing
使用周期性边界条件周期性边界，所以我们将
use periodic boundary conditions
periodic boundaries so we're putting the
弹起一个大圆圈让我们让圆圈的长度为L
springs in in a big circle
let's let the circle have a length L
这是n，所以n在圆周长度L周围有n个质量，因此K必须为2 PI
which is n so n masses around in a
circle length L so K then has to be 2 PI
在L倍上，一些整数PP是整数的元素，通常是
over L times some integer P P is an
element of integers usual way that
当我们将所有内容放入定期框中时发生，因此
happens when we put everything in a
periodic box so the total number of
然后，模式数就是看2pi的k的总范围
modes number of modes is then the total
range of k's that were looking at 2pi
在a上，这就是我们正在寻找的k的整个范围
over a so that's the entire range of k's
we're looking at
除以模式2 PI到L的间距，所以我们要做的是
divided by the spacing between modes 2
PI over L so what we're doing is we're
将自己的青铜器分成许多小块，间距为2 PI
dividing up this bronze own into lots of
little pieces whose spacing is 2 PI over
L ok，所以在a或M上为L，因此我们拥有的正常模式总数
L ok and so that is L over a or M so the
total number of normal modes that we've
解决的是n有n个正常模式，因为有n个质量开始
solved for is n there are n normal modes
because there were n masses to begin
这并不奇怪，您在学习时可能会发现
with this should not be surprising you
probably found this when you studied
质量和弹簧桩，如果您从n个质量开始，则不可避免地得到
mass and spring piles before if you
start with n masses you inevitably get
和正常模式，这实际上正是Debye之前猜到的
and normal modes and this is actually
exactly what Debye had guessed before
他想拥有与他的度数相同的模式数
that he's wanted to have just the same
number of modes as he had degrees of
他系统的自由还可以，到目前为止，我们所做的一切都是完全
freedom in his system okay so so far
everything we've done is completely
到目前为止，我们现在将继续讨论量子力学
classical so far so now we're going to
move on to quantum mechanics quantum so
在量子力学中，有一个非常简单的规则，那就是如果您有一个
in quantum mechanics there's a very
simple rule which is that if you have a
普通模式频率的经典普通模式频率欧米茄
normal mode a classical normal mode of
frequency a frequency Omega
当你进入成为本征态的量子力学时
when you go to quantum mechanics that
becomes eigenstates
能量为H bar V sub n等于H bar Omega n加1/2那么这是什么
with energy H bar V sub n equals H bar
Omega n plus 1/2 so what is this what is
这n告诉我们这n告诉我们您选择一个特定的正常模式
this n telling us this n is telling us
you pick a particular normal mode that
你在看，这个n基本上是在告诉你
you're looking at and this n is
basically telling you the amplitude of
该模式，然后，如果您让它振荡很多，那么它就有很多能量
that mode then if you if you let it
oscillate a lot it has a lot of energy
如果你允许的话，我会说一点，它只有一点能量，所以
if you let it I'll say a little bit it
has only a little bit of energy so it's
区别在于最终，但关键是能量在
the difference bein an end but the key
thing is that the energy is quantized in
H bar Omega的整数单位，这是一个重要的定义，
integer units of this H bar Omega now
this is an important definition that one
量子量子振动的振动量子是声子。
声子是声子，它完全类似于光子
phonon is a phonon phonon this is
entirely analogous to a quantum of light
作为光子，它的能量是K的h-barΩ，具体取决于哪个
being a photon and it's energy energy is
h-bar Omega of K depending on which
K实际上正在考虑，所以我现在不得不
which K were actually considering so I
now I have to I have to rant for a
关于我正常的宠物烦恼的第二件事，所以我的怒气是，如果你打开很多
second about my normal pet peeve
so my rant is that if you open up a lot
他们会告诉你，声子是振动的量子
of books they will tell you that a
phonon is a quantum of vibrational
能量或光子是光能的量子，我认为这实际上是一个坏问题
energy or a photon is a quantum of light
energy and I think that's actually a bad
定义我认为您不应该指定能量，因为光子的确是
definition I think you shouldn't specify
energy because it's true that a photon
携带光，但也携带角动量
carries light but it also carries
angular momentum it carries momentum so
你为什么要指定能量而不是仅仅而不是仅仅指定一个
why did you specify energy and not just
and not just specify this a quantum of
与声子类似地发光这里的声子
light
similarly with phonon here a phonon
携带能量，但也携带动量和其他东西，所以我
carries carries energy but it also
carries momentum and other things so I'm
只是要说一个振动量子，这就是声子，所以要说一点
just gonna say a quantum of vibration
here's the phonon so to be a little bit
通过声子更具体地说明我的意思，我们选择一个特定的
more specific about what I mean here by
by a phonon we pick a particular
模式或特定的振荡频率是特定的波矢K
mode or a particular oscillation
frequency is a particular wave vector K
然后我们说如果它处于基态N等于零，我们说那里
and then we say if if it's in this
ground state N equals zero we say there
如果您最多激发一个，就不会有声子填充该状态，我们说有一个
are no phonons filling that state if you
excite n up to one we say there's one
在这种模式下的声子，如果我们最终激发到两个，我们说其中有两个声子
phonon in that mode if we excite end up
to two we say there's two phonons in
该模式与您现在对光子和光所做的完全相似
that mode it's exactly similar to what
you do with photons and light now of
当然这些声子必须是玻色子，因为你可以把声子是玻色子
course these phonons have to be bosons
because you can put phonon is a boson is
玻色子，因为在给定的K模式下，您可以在给定模式下放置多个声子
a boson because you can put more than
one phonon in a given mode given K mode
在特定的K模式下，其声子的能量为h-bar Omega K，因此
and its energy energy of the phonons in
a particular K mode is h-bar Omega K so
这是特定K模式下声子的能量乘以玻色系数
this is the energy of the phonons in a
particular K mode times the Bose factor
还有另一个迹象表明我们在这里谈论玻色子Bose factor
there's another indication that we're
talking about bosons here Bose factor
是因子加一半，所以这里的Bose因子告诉您预期
was factor plus one half so the the Bose
factor here tells you the expected
在特定模式下，给定温度下给定声子数
number of phonons in the particular mode
had a given at a given temperature okay
每个人都很舒服吗，它看起来应该像您所做的一样
is everyone comfortable this it should
look a lot like like what you did with
光子较早是的，是的，很好，现在我们可以做什么
photons earlier yes yeah okay
good so now what we can do we can use
这些信息实际上可以计算出量子力学的热容量
this information to actually calculate
the quantum mechanical heat capacity of
我们的链现在我们的链是一个相当简化的链，这是一个简化的模型
our chain now our chain is a rather
simplified chain it's a simplified model
它发生了什么，您知道它具有这些简化吗？
of what's going on it has you know it
has these a number of simplifications
你知道泉水只在最近的邻居之间，
that you know the springs are only
between nearest neighbors and they're
完美的谐波弹簧，但经过这些简化，我们要做什么
perfectly harmonic Springs but given
those simplifications what we're going
最后给出的是热容量的精确答案
to end up with is an exact answer for
the heat capacity no approximations at
因此，对于热容量的确切答案是链中的总能量
all so the exact answer for the heat
capacity the total energy in the chain
是所有模式的总和K等于a的2 PI的负PI
is the sum over all of the modes K
equals minus PI over a 2 PI over a of
h-bar欧米茄模式Boze factor beta H bar欧米茄K加1/2的情况
h-bar Omega that mode Boze factor beta H
bar Omega K plus 1/2 where the case are
现在通常以2 PI超过L um的步骤
taken in in steps of
steps of 2 PI over L um now the usual
可以用很多次以前的方式用整数DK代替总和
way that we have before so many times we
can replace that sum with an integral DK
超过系统长度的2 pi倍，我们只需从负值进行积分
over 2 pi times the length of the system
and we only have to integrate from minus
PI超过2 PI的PI，因为一旦不在Brauns自己的范围内，我们将被读取
PI over a 2 PI over a because once were
outside the Brauns own we're just read
列举一些我们之前已经描述过的模式，以及
ascribing some of the modes that we have
already previously described and if we
计算系统中的模式总数总数模式总数
count the total number of modes in the
system total number of modes total
模式数量模式数量很好，我们可以写成L over 2
number of modes number of modes it would
be well okay we can write it as L over 2
pi L由2个PI减去2个PI减去1个DK上的2 pi积分
pi L over 2 pi integral from minus PI
over a 2 PI over a DK of the number 1 so
我们将要整合所有模式的总数
we're just gonna integrate over all the
number of modes count the total number
会给我们一个L或系统中原子数的模式
of modes that will give us what L over a
or the number of atoms in the system
这再次与Debye中断了整合的过程非常相似
which again exactly similar to what
Debye did he cut off his integration
使得他在系统中恰好有n个模式，并且没有
over modes such that he would have
exactly n modes in the system and no
不少，所以我们使用我们使用的Omega K
more no less so we use we use our Omega
of K that we derived wherever it is well
我会再写一遍，我们使用2平方根的Kappa
off the top of the board I'll write it
again we use 2 square root of Kappa over
m超过2的ka的绝对值符号，如果将其插入到那个和中
m absolute value sign of ka over 2 and
if we plug that in to that sum which we
可以变成积分，我们将获得确切的能量
can turn into an integral we will get
the exact amount of energy in that
系统，他给一个温度，您可以区分它来获取热量
system and he give a temperature and you
can differentiate it to get the heat
购买二手的容量，使ik等于B声音乘以K的绝对值，
capacity to buy used oh make ik a equals
B sound times absolute value of K which
在小K上非常吻合，但在大K上不同意，但这是一个
agrees pretty well at small K but
doesn't agree at large K but it was a
可以很好地逼近爱因斯坦，也可以用同样的方式描述爱因斯坦
pretty good approximation Einstein you
can describe Einstein the same way
爱因斯坦曾用过他所有的振荡器Omega K的相同频率Omega 0
Einstein used all his oscillators Omega
K are at the same frequency Omega 0 that
会给你爱因斯坦模型，基本上说有n个隔离子
will give you the Einstein model
basically saying there's n Isolators and
它们无论如何都具有相同的频率
they all have the same same frequency at
any rate they
使我们至少可以写下来，至少可以代数地写下来
enables us to write down at least at
least you can algebraically write it
精确地表达我们的链量子的热容
down an exact expression for exactly the
heat capacity of our chain quantum
从机械上讲，我们需要一个更重要的概念
mechanically there's one more rather
important concept that we need to
今天介绍一下，这又回到了K和K plus是
introduce today which is again coming
back to this idea that K and K plus are
在a上的倒数晶格两个pi M的成员代表同一波I
a member of the reciprocal lattice two
pi M over a represent the same wave I
意味着我们知道我们喜欢将这些声子视为新的事实
mean the fact that we you know we like
to think of these phonons as being new
粒子以与我们认为光子相同的方式思考量子
particles the same way we think of
photons as being you know quantum
力学很棒，因为您可以将事物视为粒子或波浪
mechanics is great because you can think
of things as particles or waves waves
和颗粒，然后来回走，但是你喜欢
and particles and go back and forth
however however you like
所以有时候我们喜欢把这些声子看作是波浪
so sometimes we like to think about
these phonons as being waves and
有时我们喜欢将它们视为粒子和我们喜欢的粒子
sometimes we like to think about of them
as being particles and particles we like
想一想它们是您知道某个正在移动的物体，它承载着一些
to think about them is you know some
object that's moving and it carries some
动量，实际上有时候在某些模型中，这些声子可以
amount of momentum and in fact sometimes
in some models these phonons can you
知道比这更复杂的模型
know more complicated models than this
one
但是在你的声子中它们可以以它们的方式散布到事物中
but in your phonons can can scatter into
things in their way they can scatter
进入其他声子，从其他电话中散射出来，可以从电子中散射出来
into other phonon scatter off of other
phones they can scatter off of electrons
例如，它们可以散射光，我们将讨论其中的一些
they can scatter off of light for
example and we'll discuss some of those
学期后期的事情，以及您可能认为会有一个
things later in the term and the thing
you might think that there would be a
在散射过程中保持了动量，但是我们怎么可能
conserved momentum in the scattering
process but how is it possible we can
如果K的定义不明确，则在散射过程中保持动量
conserve momentum in a scattering
process if K isn't even well-defined up
对于这一变化，K和K加G代表同一波，那么
to this change that K and K plus G
represent the same wave so what one does
是一个定义定义什么叫晶体动量晶体晶体重量
is one defines define what is known as
crystal momentum crystal crystal weight
好吧，如果是K，这是通常的事情，如果是K，则它的波矢，如果是h-bar
well okay if it's K it's the usual thing
if it's K its wave vector if it's h-bar
K它的动量为水晶动量，所以我将输入H条形的晶体动量
K its momentum crystal momentum so I'll
put in the H bars crystal momentum which
被定义为H Bar K模2pi在现在的模上是什么意思模是一个词
is defined as H Bar K modulo 2pi over a
now what's modulo mean modulo is a word
最多等于加法项的加法项，例如12 mod
which means up to additive terms of
additive terms of so for example 12 mod
5等于7 mod 5 modulo 5，因为最多5 12和7的加法项是
5 equals 7 mod 5 modulo 5 because up to
an additive term of 5 12 and 7 are the
同样的2 mod 5也一样，所以换句话说，我们就是在承认
same 2 mod 5 is also the same okay
so in other words we're we're confessing
动量在2 pi之内不能守恒
that momentum is not conserved up to
this factor of 2 pi over a that you can
取并给出您知道的2 pi的加法项的自由因子，
take and give factors you know additive
terms of 2 pi over a freely and this
可能会打扰您，因为您可能知道自己可能真的很喜欢这个东西
might disturb you because you might you
know you might really like this thing
叫做动量守恒，但是我们真的需要回想一下为什么
called momentum conservation but we
really need to think back to why is it
如果首先考虑对称性，我们首先要保持动量
that we wanted momentum conservation in
the first place if you took the symmetry
在相对论课程上学期，您会记住动量守恒
in relativity course last term you'll
remember that momentum conservation
来自空间的对称性，而来自它的空间对称性是
comes from a symmetry of space and the
symmetry of space that it came from was
空间的平移对称性，因此您可以翻译，知道自己的
translational symmetry of space and so
you can translate you know your
在太空中关注您想要的任何地方，所有物理定律仍然是
attention in space to anywhere you want
and all the laws of physics remain the
在我们的模型中相同，我们不再拥有它，因为只允许
same in our model here we don't have
that anymore because we're only allowed
我们的翻译小组翻译的内容比您知道的要小
to translate by a our translation group
is smaller than in you know in out in
这里的空间真空我们只能通过和来翻译
the vacuum of space here we can we're
only allowed to translate by a and
因此，我们得到的保护律不那么强，
because of that we get a less strong
conservation law that instead of having
动量完全守恒，我们只有动量守恒在2 pi以上
momentum completely conserved we only
have momentum conserved up to 2 pi over
好吧，这就是这里发生的事情，它与这个想法非常相似
a ok so that's what's gone gone on here
it's very similar to this idea of
诺斯里奇定理这不是完全东北定理，而是人们在说
northridge theorem it's not exactly
northeast theorem instead people talking
大约是卑鄙的话，她从
about a mean orther she was amazing a
mathematician from the early part of the
严格来说1900年代的Northridge定理仅适用于连续
1900s northridge theorem strictly
speaking only applies to continuous
对称性，这是一个离散的对称性，但是非常相似，并且
symmetries and this is a discrete
symmetry but it's very very similar and
我们获得的动量守恒能力不如您的原因
the reason we're getting less strong
momentum conservation than we had in you
知道当您想到空间中的规则粒子是因为我们不
know in in when you think about regular
particles in space is because we don't
具有相同的空间平移对称性，我们只有一个离散的
have the same translational symmetry of
space we only have a discrete
平移对称好了，我们还有几分钟，所以我要去
translational symmetry ok we have a few
minutes left so I'm going to I'm going
添加我答应过的主题
to add
subject I promised you I would address
而且那个主题是氢键，所以这是一个完全不同的主题
and that subject is hydrogen-bonding so
this is a totally different subject I'm
只是拿起它，因为它只会花我们五分钟的氢气
just picking this up because it's only
gonna take us five minutes hydrogen
氢键的一般概念是氢是非常特殊的
bonds the general idea of a hydrogen
bond is that hydrogen is a very special
元素，因为它基本上只是一个质子和一个电子，所以可能会提示
element because it's basically just a
proton and an electron so tip you might
想像一下有一个大原子，所以这里有一个像氟的大原子，然后
imagine having a big atom like so here's
a big atom like fluorine and then it
与氢原子或多或少地离子键合，但可能略微共价键合
bonds to hydrogen atom more or less
ionically but maybe slightly covalently
所以氢原子坐在这里是质子，电子是更多
so the hydrogen atom is sitting out here
it's a proton and it's electron is more
或更少地坐在这里，其电子已被吸入氟原子
or less sitting over here its electron
has been sucked to the the fluorine atom
剩下的是光子，所以这是我们的氢核
and what's been left behind is a bare
proton so this is our hydrogen nucleus
剩下的是光子质子，这是非常特别的，因为
and what's left is a bare proton proton
and that's extremely special because
这是化学界唯一一次获得裸质子的时间
it's the only time in chemistry where
you ever get a bare proton it's not
被周围的一些电子屏蔽，所以只要有化学键
screened by some electrons around it so
whenever you have chemical bonding
通常一些电子在周围移动，但是总有一些壳
usually some of the electrons are moved
around but there's always some shell
除了氢可以去除一个电子的情况外
left over except in the case of hydrogen
where the one electron can be removed
从那里，你剩下一个光子，这就是为什么氢键在
from it and you're left with a bare
proton and that's why hydrogen bonds in
非常特殊的方式，那么如果您有另一个原子发生，那将会发生什么
very special ways so what can happen
then is if you have another atom over
这里说氧或另一个氟原子，这个裸质子将
here say oxygen or maybe another
fluorine atom this bare proton will then
使这个氟原子非常强地极化并吸引它，这是
make a very strong polarization of this
fluorine atom and attract it and this is
氢键H键，是氢与另一个原子的键合
the hydrogen bond H bond which is the
bonding of the hydrogen to another atom
通过这种强大的偶极力，让我向您展示如何
via this strong dipole force so let me
show you a classic picture of this how
这表明冰是典型的例子，其中您有一个冰
this shows up so ice is sort of the
classic example of that where you have a
氢坐在氧气表面上，使您的水变成氧气
hydrogen sitting on the surface of
oxygen to make your h2o but the oxygen
基本上已经将氢中的电子去除了
has essentially removed the electrons
from the hydrogen to a very large extent
留下一个裸露的氢载体核，一个裸露的质子
leaving behind a bare hydrogen bearer
nucleus a bare proton that their proton
使另一个电子极化，并吸引另一个电子
polarizes this other electron over here
and attract this other electron here on
这种氧气并吸引氧气，为此形成非常弱的点状键
this oxygen and attracts the oxygen
making a very weak dotted bond to this
大氧气坐在这里，这你
big
oxygen sitting over here and this you
知道它是弱键，比共价键或弱键弱得多
know it's a weaker bond it's a much
weaker bond than a covalent bond or an
离子键，但足以结冰
ionic bond
but it's strong enough to freeze ice you
知道低于零，所以它是一个a，你知道这是一个足够强大的结合力，可以做一些
know below below zero so it's a you know
it's a strong enough bond to do some
有趣的是，氢键进入的另一个经典案例是生物学
interesting things another classic case
where hydrogen bonds enter is in biology
特别是DNA，如果您上学期是生物学部分，
and particularly in DNA if you took the
biology segment last term you'll
如果您现在感觉不好，就将其识别为DNA
recognize this as being DNA if you
didn't well okay now you're seeing it
这是DNA，您会看到DNA是由双链组成的，对
this is DNA and you'll see so DNA is
made up this double strand and right
在双股线的中间向下，两股线拉在一起
down the middle of the double strand
where the two strands zipped together
有一个氢键与氧键，这个键是氢键
there's a hydrogen bonded to an oxygen
this bond is the hydrogen bond the
氢实际上是与氮结合的
hydrogen is really bonded to the
nitrogen over here and it has a weak
在这里与氧键结合，您会发现存在类似的氢键
bond to the oxygen over here and you'll
see that there's a similar hydrogen bond
从这里的氢到这里的氮同样地，氢键在这里
from a hydrogen here to a nitrogen here
similarly hydrogen bonds right down here
氢键就在这里，所以氢键保持在一起
and hydrogen bonds down right here so
it's a hydrogen bond that holds together
DNA沿着拉链向下延伸，因此当您拉动DNA链时
the DNA right down down this zipping so
so when you pull the strands of DNA
分开氢键，所以我认为这就是您所需要的
apart you're breaking hydrogen bonds so
I think that's all pretty much you need
知道氢键，我想我们会完成的，我们会再次捡起
to know about hydrogen bonds and I guess
we will finish we'll pick up again
明天[鼓掌]
tomorrow
[Applause]
之间有角度，那是说如果有一个角度
yeah if there's an angle between pee
you're saying that if there's an angle
在p1到p2之间​​会有余弦Thetas等等，类似的东西
between p1 to p2 there would be cosine
Thetas and so forth and things like that
是的，但是在力量仍然具有吸引力的地方，实际上
yeah but that where the force will still
be attractive you can actually there's
书中有一个练习可以帮助您完成练习，并且您可以
there's an exercise in the book that
works you through it and you can and you
可以使所有角度正确，并且总是会出现有吸引力的好问题
can get all the angles right and it will
always come out attractive good question
但不值巧克力棒，所以还是个好问题，谢谢
but not worth the chocolate bar so but
it's still a good question thank you
无论如何，所以基本上你在一个原子上会有一点波动
anyway the so it's basically you get a
little bit of a fluctuation on one atom
它引起另一个原子的波动，它们吸引，无论是哪个原子
it causes a fluctuation the other atom
and they attract and no matter which
方向波动是响应波动在
direction the fluctuation is the
responding fluctuation is in the
相反的方向，他们总是吸引，所以你仍然可以得到一个非零
opposite direction and they always
attract so you can still get a nonzero
范德华力没有范德华力比共价离子弱得多
Van der Waals force no the van der Waals
force is much weaker than covalent ionic
或氢键，但它仍然足够强到可以引起诸如
or hydrogen bond but it's still strong
enough to cause important effects such
如您所知，它可以将低温下的氩气和
as you know you know it holds together
things like argon at low temperature and
当氩气变成固体时，范德华斯更有趣
when argon becomes a solid a more
interesting case of where van der Waals
如果你去过热带气候，部队就会和这个家伙在一起
forces show up is with this guy if
you've ever been to tropical climate
这是壁虎的小蜥蜴，他们也出售汽车保险
this this is a gecko a little lizard
they also they sell car insurance in the
美国我不知道为什么这是事实，这是美国的吉祥物
United States I don't I don't know why
that's true this is the mascot of the
壁虎Geico壁虎公司无论如何壁虎是惊人的小动物
Gecko Geico gecko company anyway
geckos are amazing little creatures
因为它们可以爬上几乎完全平坦的玻璃墙而没有
because they can crawl up almost
completely flat glass walls with no
根本没有麻烦，实际上把它们粘在墙上的东西变成了
trouble at all and the thing that
actually sticks them to the wall turns
成为范德华力，他们让你知道他们的脚很扁平，
out to be Van der Waals forces they have
you know they have very flat foot and
他们将脚踩在玻璃上，并且有足够的范德华力
they stick their foot onto the glass and
there's enough van der Waals force
在他们的脚和玻璃之间，它们是相当轻的小动物
between their foot and the glass and
they're fairly light little creatures
他们实际上可以走到墙上，因为那很好，我向我道歉
that they can actually walk up the wall
because of that all right I apologize I
过去了，我星期三见
went over it I will see you on Wednesday
you